

# **Farzad Yousefzadeh**

I'm a Software engineer working at Epic Games and living in Finland.

I'm interested in Javascript, Typescript, React, React Natve, Nodejs and Serverless.

Fascinated by DX Tooling and Automation.

Public technical speaker. Passionate about UI Engineering, Software modeling and Architecture.

Find me on Farzadyz.com / Twitter / Github / Stackoverflow / Linkedin / Medium

## **Main Tech**

HTML(5), CSS(3), Javascript(ES5+), Typescript, React, React Native, NextJS, Gatsby, NodeJS, Restful services, Serverless, Redux, Mobx, RxJS, Svelte and Sapper, Statecharts and XState, Cloud (AWS mostly), BaaS(Autho, Firebase, Amplify), CI/CD( Netlify, Heroku, GH Acons), Tesng (Cypress, Jest, MSW), SCSS/Styled components/Emoon/TailwindCSS, Build system and bundlers (Webpack, Rollup), WebSockets

## **Mobile Development**

React Native (Android and iOS), Cordova (Ionic & Phonegap)

# **Desktop**

A few experiences with ElectronJS.

#### **Databases**

MySQL, PostgreSQL, DynamoDB, Firebase Realtime DB

#### **Others**

Good at: Pair programming, Brainstorming, Code review, TDD, Git + automation + release management

<u>Mentor and Coach at MentorCruise</u>, having mentored more than 25 mentees over the course of 3 years with 5 starts rating!

Has experience working in: product companies, as a consultant, well stablished companies, startups, as a technical leader, people management, individual contributor

Has worked as an Individual contributor, Senior engineer, Lead engineer, Tech and Team leader.

Excellent at clear communication, transparency, team work, peer support, driving initiatives, driving from ideation to completion, Scoping and technical breakdown, learning, teaching, social interactions

# **Education**

BSc in Aerospace Engineering, Sharif University of Technology in Tehran Python programming, Duke University

# **Professional Experiences**

## Lead Engineer at Stately.ai

Building the next generation of software modeling tooling upon State machines and Statecharts Building XActor: A javascript framework for the actor model architecture

Building and maintaining Xstate visualizer/inspector for visualizing the application logic and event sequences

Building Stately visual editor: A drag and drop tool to build executable application logic visually and many more projects including but not limited to: The engineering blog, interactive tutorial for gamifying the learning of XState, technical documentation reworks, Building and maintaining Stately registry

# Lead Engineer at Epic Games (Nov 2019 - Jan 2021)

Core platform developer, in charge of overall architecture, engineering excellence, developer productivity and common platform services and abstractions

Technical leader of Epic Online Services in the Game Services area

Team leader, leading a team of 50

Maintainer of Epic UI, an in-house design system and component library, Developer portal and Organization portal projects

Driving the automated testing initiative across several distributed teams in Epic Games (1 year)

Driving the feature lifecycle initiative with the purpose of standardizing the life cycle of a feature
from the ideation stage to the delivery and maintenance stage, optimizing for documentation/edge
case exposure early on/cross team syncing

# Senior Software engineer at Futurice (Nov 2018 - Nov 2019)

Fullstack web engineering

Building mobile application solutions for one of the popular payment systems (Smartum) in the Nordic

Leading a team of 10 to rebuild 2 of the most popular news delivery systems, IS and HS, (with the scale of millions of visitors per day) in Finland

Building a hardware to software management system for a famous and known gaming company (Supercell) in Finland

#### Senior Web Engineer at Smarp (May 2018 - Nov 2018)

Using Angularjs and React

Maintaining a legacy product (Social Network) and Developing the new product, migrating logical parts

Migrate legacy code into new codebase (React, Redux, Webpack)

Create API Client abstraction on top of Smarp's core API to handle API data models, data interfaces, custom data selectors/transformers, Testability

Refactoring and consolidating the translation mechanism on the web and mobile clients on Smarp product

Sketching the new notification system into an Event sourcing mechanism

Planning the new design system initiative, working closely with the Design and the UX team for better E2E and integration testing coverage, solid design components, documentation, and right abstractions

Scrum, Kanban, Agile values, Teamwork, Internal tech events

Project manager of the Engineering blog

Member of the hiring committee

# [CONTRACT] Lead Javascript Engineer and Consultant at Beeptunes (Oct 2017 - May 2018)

Tech leading and developing on a shared mobile-web React application (similar to Spotify), meant to play and stream audio tracks, albums, artists

Written in React and Redux, uses a core package which shares logic and components - between React and, React Native, and probably Electron (in future)

Uses modern Javascript development environment

Teaching React, Redux, Modern Javascript and Testing best practices to the tech team

## Senior Frontend Engineer at Talos Digital (Jul 2017 - May 2018)

Maintaining the US and Mexican based company's online digital service for managing the entire Real Estate industry including All the legal access roles, legal document management, and legal process audit

AngularJS, PhantomJS, Karma, Jasmine

Passenger1 flight and accommodation booking system using React, Redux, Firebase, Jest, and Enzyme.

Agile, Scrum

# Frontend Engineer and ScrumMaster at PersianGig (Sep 2016 - Sep 2017)

Reworked multiple B2C and B2B cloud services (cloud storage, cloud-ware) from Dojo Toolkit to React and Redux

Because of better UX, being responsive for mobile users and increase in performance, our customers grew up to 1 million and 450 thousand (45% growth)

Upgraded a direct HTTP upload service to a Node.js, concurrent, chunk enabled uploader

Since the service is more reliable and supports link resumes, drag and drop and folder upload, our

upload instances grew up to almost **20,000** instances per day and decreased the number of tickets

complaining about failed uploads, hence caused a better situation for our customer support team

#### (logs indicate a 60% growth in upload usage)

Add testing to projects up to a reasonable code coverage to increase consistency and avoid common mistakes. Before that, the codebase didn't have any

Introduced Git Flow to the dev team that decreased the number of conflicts and increased development speed on the codebase

Gathered a small team of developers to run daily workshops on tech topics such as CI, DevOps, etc to make sure everybody learns as a team.

Mentored a junior frontend developer through a solid educational program (which I designed) and prepared them for team projects

Enhanced the CI pipeline to cache none-updated assets that decreased the frontend build duration up to **50%** 

Integrated upload interface with the native camera to increase UX

Designed and developed an embedding system for cloud-based files

Came up with an ACL system on projects that helped the company to reuse code base and extend its business model from B2C to B2B that eventually led to a **200,000 Euros** worth contract with the main telecommunication service in Iran called Irancell

Reworked file preview/download service to Node.js server-side rendered pages

#### Web Developer at Bertina Co. (Dec 2014 - Sep 2016)

Developed Employees Portal using AngularJS, a service to manage employees, request for vacatons, etc

Developed Minisite, a service to provide minimal, responsive personal portals with various themes and live editing using AngularJS, jQuery, and SCSS

Developed Chia, an Android application with a gamification approach to learning the English Language, including different levels, payments, live competitions using jQuery, Cordova, Socket.io and Node.js

Developed Hamkalam, an IM application for Android devices providing an anonymous chat service to the public using AngularJS, Node.jS, and MySQL

Developed CartoonLand, an Android application providing cartoons for kids, streaming online videos with multiple qualities, download manager to cache downloaded videos, user management, IAB for payments using jQuery, Cordova, PHP, MySQL

Developed multiple enterprises and personal responsive websites using Wordpress, jQuery, AngularJS

Member of the hiring process.

## Junior web development freelancing (Aug 2011 - Dec 2014)

# **Conference Talks and Meetups**

The Actor Model: a new mental model for React @React Finland 2021

So you think you know state management? @Turku frontend 2020

Experiments with State machines and Overmind @Christian Alfoni

A hitchhiker's guide to Svelte JS @HelsinkiJS Meetup 2019

In Pursuit of Finite States @SkyHacks Poland 2019

The art of explicit and consistent user interfaces v2 @HolysJS Moscow 2019

Tackle React component complexity using Reactive Statecharts @ReactJS Day Italy 2019

The art of explicit and consistent user interfaces @404Fest 2019

Introduction to modeling with Finite state machines @GDG Helsinki 2019

Explicitness and Consistency in UI @Futurice Tech weeklies 2019

React Hooks vs Reactive Statecharts @TampereJS 2019

React Hooks vs Reactive Statecharts @React Helsinki June 2019

Abstract component modeling in React @React Finland 2019

Statecharts driven UI development @ReactJS community 2019

Boost state containment with Redux Observables @React Helsinki 2019

Headless React @ReactJS Community 2018

React without React @Futurice Tech weeklies 2018

Test Driven Development @Software Talks 2018

The state of Frontend development @Software Talks 2018

The life of a software developer in Finland @CoderConf 2018

Guest at @webbidevaus podcast

Guest at @Devchat (React Roundup)

Guest at @Devchat (My Javascript story)



Technical reviewer of Learn React Hooks book by Packt